<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pensamentos de um Dinossauro (Posts about bioinformatics)</title><link>https://biraneves.github.io/pdud/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://biraneves.github.io/pdud/en/categories/bioinformatics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:biraneves@gmail.com"&gt;Ubirajara Neves&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 10:15:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Introduction to Bioinformatics: How Computing is Revolutionizing Biology</title><link>https://biraneves.github.io/pdud/en/posts/introducao-a-bioinformatica-como-a-computacao-esta-revolucionando-a-biologia/</link><dc:creator>Ubirajara Neves</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
In an increasingly digital world, it is impressive to see how computing has impacted different areas of life and knowledge. In my opinion,
one of the most fascinating areas of this intersection is bioinformatics. If you have ever wondered how computing and biology can work
together to solve complex problems, this article is for you.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdf37c15" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdf37c15"&gt;What is Bioinformatics?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdf37c15"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a nutshell, bioinformatics is the application of computational techniques to the understanding and organization of biological
information. Here, mathematics, statistics, and computer science come together to analyze and interpret biological data such as
DNA sequences, protein structures, and metabolic pathways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org5ec94ba" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5ec94ba"&gt;How did it all begin?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5ec94ba"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bioinformatics is not exactly new. The term was coined in the 1970s, but it gained traction in the 1990s with the &lt;b&gt;Human Genome Project&lt;/b&gt;
(I was in my undergraduate biology degree at the time). This colossal project required unprecedent data processing power to map and
understand the entire human genome! That's when bioinformatics proved to be indispensable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga371bf7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga371bf7"&gt;Practical applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga371bf7"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org010e0e7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org010e0e7"&gt;Medical research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org010e0e7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bioinformatics plays a crucial role in personalized medicine. By analysing individual genomes, it is possible to predict susceptibility
to certains diseases and even adapt treatments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org474ee04" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org474ee04"&gt;Agriculture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org474ee04"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In agriculture, bioinformatics helps to create more resilient and productive crops by interpreting the genomes of different plant
species.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga31a1b5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga31a1b5"&gt;Conservation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga31a1b5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bioinformatics is also applied to species conservation, helping to understand the genetics of at-risk populations and guiding conservation
efforts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc44a413" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc44a413"&gt;Challenges and opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc44a413"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like any emerging field, bioinformatics faces challenges, such as the integration of data from diverse sources and the need for increasingly
efficient algorithms. However, the opportunities are vast and the potential impact on society is immense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org680cffa" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org680cffa"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org680cffa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bioinformatics is an exciting field that lies at the intersection of several disciplines. The power of computing is shaping the future of
biology and the possibilities are virtually endless. If you are like me, passionate about biology and computing, there is no better
time to start exploring this field.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
—
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is the first post of this blog. My goal here is to record what I am studying, the knowledge I am acquiring, and the discoveries
that are crossing my path. The focus will be on bioinformatics, but I will also navigate through supporting areas such as data science,
statistics, and computer science. I hope to have you as a frequent reader, and we will meet again in the next post!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bioinformatics</category><guid>https://biraneves.github.io/pdud/en/posts/introducao-a-bioinformatica-como-a-computacao-esta-revolucionando-a-biologia/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 22:30:34 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>